Register of the Wayne S. Vucinich Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Wayne S. Vucinich Collection
1881-1994
80068
Vucinich, Wayne S.
5 manuscript boxes (2.0 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection contains reports, minutes, dispatches, and translations of and extracts from dispatches, relating to conditions in Yugoslavia, Bulgaria, and other areas of the Balkans and Eastern Europe before and during World War II, and especially to World War II resistance movements. Issuing agencies include the United States Office of Strategic Services Research and Analysis Branch, the United States Department of State, and Allied occupation authorities in Bulgaria.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Wayne S. Vucinich collection, 1926-1995, Special Collections and University Archives, Stanford University
Biographical Note
1913 Born in Butte, Montana
1918-1928 After his parents' death, Vucinich lived in his parents' village of Orah, near Bileće, in Bosnia and Herzegovina, Yugoslavia
1929 Returned to America to live with his godfather's family in Wilmington, California
1936 BA, University of California Berkeley, History and Slavic language
1936-1937 MA, University of California Berkeley, dissertation on Serbian foreign policy 1903-1909
1937-1938 Doctoral research at the Charles University in Prague, Czechoslovakia
1939 Returned to UC Berkeley after the Munich crisis interrupted his research; appointed teaching assistant in the Department of History
1941 PhD, University of California Berkeley, dissertation on Serbian political and diplomatic history in the decade preceeding World War I
1942 Married Sara 'Sally'; joined the Office of Strategic Services (OSS), Research and Analysis Branch
1943 Sent to OSS headquarters in Bari, Italy; assigned to research the Balkans
1944 Served as a liaison officer, interpreter, and Balkan expert attached to the Allied Control Council in Sofia, Bulgaria
1945-1946 Continued work on Balkan affairs for the U.S. State Department in Washington, DC
1946 Instructor, Western civilization and East European history at Stanford University
1950 Cleared and confirmed as a "Loyal American" at a hearing before the Naval Security Board
1954 Author, Serbia between East and West: The Events of 1903-1908, Stanford University Press
1955 Received the American Historical Association's George Louis Beer prize
1956 Promoted to full professor at Stanford University
1972-1985 Named director of the Center for Russian and Eastern European Studies, Stanford University
1974-1977 Curator of the Russian and East European Collection at the Hoover Institution
1977 Appointed the Robert and Florence McDonnell Professor of Eastern European Studies at Stanford, a chair established for him
1978 Formally retired
1981-1982 Served as president of the American Association for the Advancement of Slavic Studies, which established the Vucinich Book Prize in his honor in 1982
2005 Died in Menlo Park, California
Sources:
Vucinich, Wayne S., Memories of My Childhood in Yugoslavia, edited by Larry Wolff, The Society for the Promotion of Science and Scholarship, Inc., Palo Alto, California, 2007
Wayne S. Vucinich (1913-2005)- A professor between Herzegovina and California by Ivo Banac, Published in Dani (Sarajevo), 29 April 2005
Wayne S. Vucinich, Father of East European Studies, Died at 91. http://www.i-newswire.com/wayne-s-vucinich-father-of-east/a17703
Memorial Resolution, Wayne S. Vucinich. http://facultysenate.stanford.edu/memorial_resolutions/Vucinich_Wayne_SenD6020.pdf
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is comprised of reports, minutes, telegrams, notes, translations of and extracts from dispatches relating to the Austrian administration of Bosnia-Herzegovina prior World War I, and World War II in Yugoslavia and Bulgaria, particularly resistance movements in Yugoslavia and the exiled Yugoslav government.
The Bosnia-Herzegovina materials provide records of the Austrian administration of Bosnia and Herzegovina, including the crisis in 1881-1882, and political tensions in 1913-1914.
The World War II in Yugoslavia files provide documentation on the politics of the Royal Yugoslav government in exile and its active role in the Yugoslav resistance movement and the formation of a new Yugoslavia, as well as Allied countries' diplomatic activities during wartime
The United States Department of State situation reports summarize information concerning domestic political and economic developments and international affairs in the Balkans and Central and Eastern Europe during and after World War II.
The Bulgaria materials provide detailed information on Bulgarian political life and Bulgarian government between 1944 and 1946 in reports from the United States Office of Strategic Services Research and Analysis Branch, the United States Department of State, and Allied occupation authorities in Bulgaria.
The Balkans in the 1990s materials document the international community's concerns on issues during the 1990s surrounding the referendum on independence in Bosnia-Herzegovina in 1992, the events in Dr. Mirtin Horvat Hospital, Rovinj, and the leadership of the Serbian Orthodox church in Serbia.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Secret service--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Balkan Peninsula.; World War, 1939-1945--Europe, Eastern.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia--History--Axis occupation, 1941-1945.; Yugoslavia--History.; Bosnia and Herzegovina, 1903-1908.; World War, 1939-1945--Bulgaria.; United States. Office of Strategic Services. Research and Analysis Branch.; United States. Dept. of State.
Collection Contents
- Bosnia-Herzegovina materials, 1881-1914 (Box 1)
  Includes reports and government documents relating to political tensions during the Austrian administration of Bosnia-Herzegovina.
  Arranged by topic
  - Austrian administration of Bosnia-Herzegovina documents, 1881-1882 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Austria-Hungary and Bosnia-Herzegovina reports on tensions, 1913-1914 (Folder 1: 1)
- Yugoslavia in World War II files, 1940-1947 (Box 1-2)
  Consists of reports, notes, and correspondence documenting political situations, resistance movements, partisans, Tito, and Draža Mihailović.
  Arranged by subject
  - Communist and Yugoslav government, 1941-1942 (Folder 1: 3)
    Includes reports on Yugoslav resistance and developments
  - General Draža Miahilović's situation reports to the Yugoslav prime minister, 1942 (Folder 1: 4)
  - General Miahilović's contacts in London and Cairo, 1942 (Folder 1: 5)
  - General Miahilović's revolutionary movement, Belgrade, 1943 (Folder 1: 6)
  - John Biddle notes on Yugoslavia and General Miahilović, 1943 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Sava Kosanović telegrams reporting on Yugoslav politics, 1941-1943 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Economic conditions in Yugoslavia, 1943 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Tito and the resistance movement, 1944 (Folder 1: 10-12)
  - American independent military mission to Marshal Tito, 1944 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Memorandum on policy towards Yugoslavia, 1944 (Folder 1: 14)
    Includes information on resistance movements
  - Siniša Pazarec correspondence, 1945 (Folder 1: 15)
    Includes correspondence with Konstantin Fotich and Anić Srećko
  - Prince Paul correspondence, 1940-1943 (Folder 2: 1)
    Includes correspondence with Dimitrije Ljotić, Steed Green, Watson Wickham, and Seton Watson
  - Proposal on the Greek-Yugoslav union and Balkan union, 1943 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Bailey report on Peter II, King of Yugoslavia's visit to the Mediterranean, 1944 (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Gray Book" on the independent Croatian state and guerrilla movements in Croatia, 1941-1942 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Slovenia and Yugoslavia situation reports, 1942-1943 (Folder 2: 5-7)
  - Yugoslav prisoners in camps in Italy, 1943 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Yugoslav and U.S. cooperative mission for the rescue of U.S. aviators, 1944 (Folder 2: 9)
- United States Department of State situation reports, 1942-1946 (Box 2-3)
  Contains reports, press releases, and statements.
  Arranged in three groups: regional reports, country reports, and incoming telegrams
  - Regional reports, 1945-1946 (Folder 2)
    - Balkan region, including Albania, Bulgaria, Greece, Romania, and Yugoslavia, 1945-1946 (Folder 2: 10-15)
    - Central Europe region, including Germany, Austria, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, and Poland, 1946 (Folder 3: 1)
    - Eastern Europe region, including Germany, Albania, Bulgaria, Finland, Greece, Hungary, Romania, Yugoslavia, 1946 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Reports by country, 1942-1946 (Folder 3)
    - Albania, 1945-1946 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Bulgaria, 1945 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Czechoslovakia, 1945-1946 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Greece, 1944-1945 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Hungary, 1944 (Folder 3: 7)
    - Romania, 1944-1945 (Folder 3: 8)
    - Serbia, 1942 (Folder 3: 9)
    - Yugoslavia, 1943-1945 (Folder 3: 10)
  - U.S. Department of State incoming telegrams, 1946 (Folder 3: 11)
    Includes press releases on situation reports documenting economic and political situations in Albania, Czechoslovakia, and Greece
- Bulgaria materials, 1944-1947 (Box 4-5)
  Contains reports, telegrams, minutes, and notes on political affairs in Bulgaria.
  Arranged by physical form or title
  - Reports, telegrams, and notes, 1944 (Folder 4: 1-11)
    Includes daily reports on the political and private affairs of Bulgarians
  - U.S. Department of State incoming telegrams, 1945-1946 (Folder 5: 1-2)
    Includes press releases documenting reports on political and economic developments in Bulgaria
  - Nikola Petkov reports on communist activities, 1945 (Folder 5: 3)
  - Allied Control Commission (ACC) meeting minutes, 1945-1947 (Folder 5: 4-9)
    Concerns ACC activities in Bulgaria
  - "History of Allied Control Commission in Bulgaria,", 1946 (Folder 5: 10)
- Balkans in the 1990s materials, 1991-1994 (Box 5)
  Consists of reports and a publication.
  - Serbian Orthodox Church leadership publication, 1991 (Folder 5: 11)
  - "Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe" report, 1992 (Folder 5: 12)
    Concerns the referendum in Bosnia and Herzegovina
  - Croatian Helsinki Committee for Human Rights (CHC) report on the events at the Dr. Martin Horvat Hospital, in Rovinj, Croatia, 1994 (Folder 5: 13)